[{"question":"The pigments that gives class-rhodophyceae (red  algae) its distinctive red colour are:","a":"(a) Chlorophyll-a, b & phycoerythrin","b":"(b) Chlorophyll-a, c & fucoxanthin","c":"(c) Chlorophyll-a, d & phycoerythrin","d":"(d) Chlorophyll-a,c and phycocyanin","hint":"The pigments that give class-Rhodophyceae (red algae) its distinctive red colour is chlorophyll-a, d. These pigments are photosynthetic in nature and are located in the chromatophores. The other pigments present are B-carotene, xanthophylls. phycocyanin (blue in colour) and biliprotein","correct":"c"},{"question":"The dominant stage in Spirogyra is the sporophytic stage. ","a":"(a) It is correct","b":"(b) It is incorrect","c":"(c) Spirogyra does not display alternation of  generation ","d":"(d) Sometimes (a) and (b)","hint":"The dominant stage in Spirogyra is the gametophytic stage. The sporophyte is a single cell zygote","correct":"b"},{"question":"What is the similarity between gymnosperms  and angiosperms","a":"(a) Phloem of both have companian cells.","b":"(b) Endosperm is formed before fertilisation in both","c":"(c) Origin of ovule and seed is similar in both","d":"d) Both have leaves, stem and roots.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which one of the following is the major difference between mosses and ferns? ","a":"a) Ferns lack alternation of generation while mosses shows the same","b":"b) Mosses are facultative aerobes while ferns are obligates aerobes","c":"(c) Vascular bundles of ferns show xylemvessels while those of mosses lack it.","d":"(d) Sporophytes of ferns live much longer compared to the sporophytes of mosses","hint":"Mosses and ferns belong to bryophytes and  pteridophytes respectively. In bryophytes, the dominant phase in the life cycle is the gametophytic plant body. However, in pteridophytes, the main plant body is a sporophyte, which is differentiated into true root, stem and leaves. These organs possess well-differentiated vascular tissues","correct":"d"},{"question":"Gemma cups are small receptacles that give rise  to gemmae (asexual buds). These gemma cups are found in","a":"a) Sphagnum and Marchantia","b":"(b) Marchantia","c":"(c) Funaria","d":"(d) Fern","hint":"Asexual reproduction in Marchantia occurs by the formation of gemmae. They are multicellular, green and biconvex lens shaped bodies that are produced in gemma cups. On detaching from the gemma cup, they germinate to produce new plants.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Number of cotyledons in Zea mays, Cycas and Pinus respectively are:","a":"(a) 1,2,4","b":"(b) 1,2, many","c":"(c) 2,2, many","d":"(d) 2,1,4","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Mosses and ferns are found places because both in moist and shady","a":"a) require presence of water for fertilisation","b":"(b) do not need sunlight for photosynthesis","c":"(c) depend for their nutrition on micro-organisms  which can survive only at low temperature.","d":"(d) cannot compete with sun-loving plants.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The main plant body in pteridophyte is:","a":"(a) sporophyte (2n) which is differentiated into root, stem and leaf.","b":"(b) gametophyte (n) which is differentiated into root, stem and leaf. ","c":"(c) sporophyte having no root, stem and leaf.","d":"d) gametophyte having no root but only stem and leaf","hint":"The main plant body in pteridophytes is  sporophyte (2n) which is differentiated into root (2n), stem and leaf ","correct":"a"},{"question":"The ploidy level of protonema, apophysis.  calyptra and perichactial leaves in Funaria are:","a":"a) N, 2N, N and 2N respectively","b":"(b) 2N, N, N and 2N respectively","c":"(c) 2N, 2N, N and N respectively","d":"d) N, 2N, N and N respectively","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Bryophytes can be separated from algae because they","a":"(a) are thalloid forms.","b":"(b) have no conducting tissue","c":"(c) possess archegonia with outer layer of sterile cells","d":"(d) contain chloroplasts in their cells.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The rhizophore is not a true root because it is:","a":"(a) Endogenous","b":"b) Exogenous","c":"(c) Mesogenous","d":"(d) Endarch","hint":"The rhizophore is not a true root because it  is exogenous","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following occurs both in fresh as  well as in marine water?","a":"(a) Oedogonium","b":"(b) Cladophora","c":"c) Spirogyra","d":"(d) None of the above","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ectocarpus, Dictyota, Laminaria, Sargassum,  and Fucus belong to the class:","a":"(a) Rhodophyceae","b":"(b) Pheophyceae","c":"(c) Cyanophyceae","d":"(d) Chlorophyceae","hint":"Ectocarpus. Dictyota, Laminaria, Sargassum and Fucus belong to the class Phaeophyceae.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is living fossil?","a":"(a) Pinus","b":"(b) Ginkgo biloba","c":"(c) Thuja","d":"(d) Deodar","hint":") Presence of Ginkgo biloba, a gymnosperm, is confined to the eastern part of China and japan","correct":"b"},{"question":"In some of the liverworts, there are special elongated cells called claters that possess a helical thickening of the cell wall. As elaters lose water, they shrink longitudinally and compress the helical thickening like a spring. When the stress reaches a critical point, the compressed \"spring\" snaps back to its resting position liberating hundreds of in all directions.","a":"(a) Moisture particles","b":"(b) Spores","c":"(c) Sperm","d":"(d) Ova","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which one of the following is of consider ableeconomic importance? ","a":"(a) Riccia","b":"b) Funaria","c":"(c) Marchantia","d":"d) Sphagnum","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In gymnosperm, endosperm is formed by:","a":"(a) fusion between a male gamete and  two polar nuclei ","b":"(b) fusion between a male gamete and a polar nuclei ","c":"(c) fusion between egg and male gamete","d":"(d) germination of megaspore","hint":"In gymnosperms, the endosperm is formed in the ovule during germination of the megaspore, it consequently becomes the female prothallus (gametophyte), with a haploid set of chromosomes. The archegonia in gymnosperms develop from","correct":"d"},{"question":"Botanical snakes\" are","a":"(a) Algae","b":"(b) Fungi","c":"(c) Bryophytes","d":"(d) Pteridophytes","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The plant body constituting a holdfast, stipe and frond are seen in:","a":"(a) Volvox","b":"(b)  Chara","c":"c) Laminaria","d":"(d)  Chlamydomonas","hint":"Laminaria belong to the class Phaeophyceae. Plant body of Laminaria is generally attached to the substratum by a holdfast which has a stalk, the stipe and frond which","correct":"c"},{"question":"During monsoon, ground becomes slippery  (d)  Chlamydomonas  because of:  ","a":"(a) Red algae","b":"b) Blue-green algae","c":"(c) Mosses","d":"(d) Liverworts","hint":"During monsoon, ground becomes slippery","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following part of the Funaria,  sporophyte is involved in the dispersal of spores","a":"(a) Calyptra","b":"(b) Peristome","c":"(c) Operculum","d":"(d) Annulus","hint":"Peristome is a ring of teeth around opening of the capsule in mosses (Funaria).","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following part of the Funaria,  sporophyte is involved in the dispersal of spores?","a":"(a) Calyptra","b":"b) Peristome","c":"c) Operculum","d":"(d) Annulus","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Canada balsam is obtained from:","a":"(a) Pinus wallichiana","b":"(b) Abies balsamea","c":"(c) Gnetum gnemon","d":"d) Ephedra vulgaris","hint":"Canada balsam is a resin obtained Abies balsamea. The liquid is viscous,  from  yellowish and greenish in colour. The  principal use of canada balsam is for  mounting microscopic slides and as a","correct":"b"},{"question":"When moss spores germinate, they form:","a":"(a) Leafy gametophyte","b":"(b) Capsule","c":"(c) Protonema","d":"(d) Rhizoids","hint":"When moss spores germinate, they form protonema","correct":"c"},{"question":"Fern plant is a:","a":"(a) Haploid gametophyte","b":"(b) Diploid gametophyte","c":"(c) Diploid sporophyte","d":"(d) Haploid sporophyte","hint":"Fern plant is a diploid sporophyte","correct":"c"},{"question":"A bryophytic plant has chromosome number 9. Chromosome number in spores and protonema will be","a":"(a) 9 & 9","b":"(b) 18 & 18","c":"(c) 27 & 18","d":"d) 9 & 18","hint":"Spores are formed after meiosis in diploid  cells and protonema by their germination  where nuclear divisions are mitotic only.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Heterothallism is a term used for the symbiosis of","a":"(a) Algae and Cycas","b":"(b) Algae and Fungi","c":"(c) Virus and Algae","d":"(d) Fungi and Pinus","hint":"Heterothallism is a condition found in between algae and fungi in which sexual reproduction occurs only between genetically different self-incompatible mating types (strains) of","correct":"b"},{"question":"Cycas has two cotyledons but is not included  under angiosperms because it has:","a":"(a) Circinate ptyxis","b":"(b) Compound leaves","c":"(c) Monocot like stem","d":"(d) Naked seeds","hint":"In Cycas, seeds are naked because they are not covered by overy","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which one of the following is correct","a":"a) Protonema of moss and prothallus of Dryopteris are sporophytic","b":"(b) Protonema of moss and prothallus of Dryopteris are gametophytic","c":"(e) Moss protonema is sporophytic, Pteris  prothallus is gametophytic but plant body of Pteris and Funaria are gametophytic","d":"d) Plant body of moss is gametophytic while  Dryopteris is, both gametophytic and sporophytic","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Bryophytes are different from fungi in having:","a":"(a) Land habit","b":"(b) Sterile jacket layers","c":"(c) Multiflagellate gametes","d":"(d) Gametophytic plant body","hint":"Bryophytes are different from fungi in having sterile jacket layers","correct":"b"},{"question":"The characteristic trait of the plant body of bryophtyes is that: ","a":"(a) plant body is more differentiated than that of alage","b":"b) plant body is equally differentiated to that of alage","c":"(c) plant body is less differentiated than that of alage","d":"d) plant body is not differentiated","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The most common type of spore produced during asexual reproduction of algae is: ","a":"(a) Aplanospore","b":"(b)  Endospore","c":"c) Zoospore","d":"d) Oospore","hint":"Zoospores are the most common type of  spores produced during asexual reproduction  in algae. These spores are flagellated and  thus motile, which gives rise to a new plant","correct":"c"},{"question":"Fruits are not formed in gymnosperms because of","a":"(a) Absence of pollination","b":"b) Absence of seed","c":"(c) Absence of fertilisation","d":"d) Absence of ovary","hint":"Fruits are not formed in gymnosperms because of absence of ovary ","correct":"d"},{"question":"The pyrenoids are made up of","a":"a) proteinaceous centre and starchy sheath","b":"(b) core of protein surrounded by fatty sheath","c":"c) core of starch surrounded by sheath of protein","d":"d) core of nucleic acid surrounded by protein sheath","hint":"The pyrenoids are small spherical protein bodies surrounded by starch deposition. They are found singly or in numbers embedded in the chloroplast of many algae","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is known as pond scum?","a":"(a) Volvox","b":"(b) Ulothrix","c":"c) Nostoc","d":"(d) Spirogyra","hint":"Spirogyra is a fresh water green algae. It is also known as pond scum, pond silk or water silk","correct":"d"},{"question":"Female reproductive part of bryophytes is:","a":"(a) Antheridium","b":"(b) Oogonium","c":"(c) Archegonium","d":"d) Sporangium","hint":"Female sex organ is called archegonium which is flask shaped with a tubular neck and a swollen venter.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Pollination of pollen grains in Pinus takes place at","a":"(a) One celled stage","b":"(b) Two celled stage","c":"(c) Three celled stage","d":"(d) Four celled stage","hint":"Pollination in Pins takes place when two prothallial cells, one generative cell and one tube cell are formed. i.e. four celled stage","correct":"d"},{"question":"Chlorophyll and chloroplast are present in spores of:","a":"(a) Lycopodium","b":"(b) Azolla","c":"(c) Dryopteris","d":"(d) Marsillea","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Cycas and Ginkgo are regarded as primitive gymnosperms because","a":"(a) they are lacking cones.","b":"(b) they need water for fertilisation","c":"c) they are living fossils","d":"(d) they have ciliated sperms","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is/are grouped under phanerograms?","a":"(a) Angiosperms","b":"(b) Gymnosperms","c":"(c) Pteridophytes","d":"(d) Both (a) and (b)","hint":"","correct":"d"}]